A Finding Aid to the James D. Smillie and Smillie family papers, 1853-1957, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- George Smillie Papers, 1867-1920; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 5-6
  - Printed Material, 1872-1913; 3.4; Archival Resource Key
    Found are clippings of articles written by George Smillie and reproductions of works of art.
    - Clippings, 1913; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Reproductions of Works of Art, 1872; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Oversized Clippings scanned with Box 5, Folder 30, 1913; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, 1880-circa 1920; 3.5; Archival Resource Key
    Found are portraits of George Smillie, Smillie in his studio, family portraits and snapshots including children, photographs of his home and studio at Ridgefield, and other unidentified houses.
    - George H. Smillie, circa 1880-1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - George H. Smillie in Studio, circa 1890; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 33)
      Oversized material housed in Box 6, Folder 3
    - George H. Smillie Family, circa 1889-circa 1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 34-36)
    - Outdoors, circa 1900; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Studio at Ridgefield, circa 1900; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Ridgefield House, circa 1900; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Unidentified Homes and Interiors, 1898-circa 1900; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 40)
      Likely the Smillie's Cohasset home.
    - Oversized photo of George H. Smillie in Studio scanned with Box 5, Folder 33, circa 1890; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Helen Jacobs Smillie Papers, 1860-1910; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 5
  Found are scattered correspondence and photographs.
  4.1: Correspondence, 1860-1906
  4.2: Photographs, circa 1870s-1910
  - Correspondence, 1860-1906; 4.1; Archival Resource Key
    Found are letters from Smille's mother, father, and husband, George H. Smillie.
    - Jacobs, Samuel, 1860; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Jacobs, Mrs. Samuel, circa 1894; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Smillie, George, 1894; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Illegible, 1906; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Photographs, 1870-1910; 4.2; Archival Resource Key
    Found are portraits of Helen Jacobs Smillie.
    - Helen Jacobs Smillie, circa 1870-1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 45)
- Other Family Members, circa 1880s-1957; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 5
  There are materials relating to other members of the Smillie Family, including the children of George and Helen Jacobs Smillie--Sheldon, Charles, Gordon, and William Smillie.
  The series is arranged as 3 subseries.
  5.1: Correspondence, 1895-1943
  5.2: Personal Business Records, 1957
  5.3: Photographs, 1880-circa 1910
  - Correspondence, 1895-1943; 5.1; Archival Resource Key
    Found are two pieces of correspondence to Gordon Smillie and Charles Smillie.
    - Grandma Jacobs to Charles Smillie, 1895; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Walter Pierce to Gordon Smillie, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Personal Business Records, 1957; 5.2; Archival Resource Key
    Found is a list of works of art by Smillie family members.
    - Lists of Works of Art by Smillie Family Members, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Photographs, 1880-circa 1910; 5.3; Archival Resource Key
    Found is Sheldon Smillie's scrapbook of photographs that depict exteriors and interiors of homes in Cohassett and Westport Point; landscapes; works of art by George Smillie; family members; disasters and tragedies in New York City including the Windsor Hotel fire, a fire at the Pulitzer residence, and the collapse of a shore wall at the navy yard in Brooklyn; and weddings and other family events. There is also a portrait of William Smillie.
    - Sheldon Smillie's Scrapbook, 1898-circa 1910; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Unknown Portrait, circa 1898; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 50)
      Photograph tucked into scrapbook.
    - William Smillie, circa 1880s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 51)